Tom Gehrels Papers, 1894-2011 (bulk 1961-2000)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Tom Gehrels Papers, 1804-2011 (bulk 1960-2000)
MS 541
Gehrels, Tom
Tom Gehrels Papers, 1894-2010 (Bulk 1960-2000). This collection is comprised of mostly professional papers and some personal papers of Dutch/American astronomer Tom Gehrels. The bulk of the material relates to his career as a professor and astronomical researcher at the University of Arizona.
25 linear ft.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/ E-Mail: LBRY-askspcoll@email.arizona.edu
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Tom Gehrels was born Anton M. J. Gehrels in Haarlemmermeer, the Netherlands on February 21, 1925. As a teenager, after Nazi Germany invaded the Netherlands in 1939, Gehrels became active in the Dutch Resistance. He later escaped to England where he received further training and was sent back by parachute to his native country as an organizer for Britain’s Special Operations Executive (SOE) which committed sabotage and spied on the German forces.
After the war he attended the University of Leiden where he graduated with a degree in physics and astronomy in 1951. He continued his education at the University of Chicago where he obtained his doctorate in astronomy and astrophysics in 1956. Dr. Gehrels was a research associate at Indiana University and McDonald Observatory for five years where he pioneered the first photometric system for asteroids.
In 1961 he joined Dr. Gerard Kuiper at the University of Arizona where he was one of the first members of the Lunar and Planetary Laboratory and a faculty member of the Department of Planetary Sciences and Astronomy. Gehrels remained at the University for the next 50 years until his death in 2011.
While at the University of Arizona Dr. Gehrels developed a program of photolarimetry. His studies led to the discovery and interpretation of wavelength dependence on the polarization of light from a variety of objects. He was the principle investigator for the team that created the imaging photo-polarimeters for Pioneers 10 and 11 and the 1st flybys of Jupiter and Saturn in the 1970s.
He participated in the discovery of over 4000 asteroids. This was done in a sky survey using the 48-inch Schmidt telescope at Palomar Observatory in California and shipping the plates to two Dutch astronomers at Leiden Observatory, in the Netherlands who analyzed them for new asteroids. Gehrels also discovered a number of comets
Dr.Gerhels also developed and taught introductory astronomy courses that were popular with non-science undergraduates. Besides teaching at the University of Arizona he also lectured at the Physical Researh Laboratory in Ahmedabad (India), where he was a Lifetime Fellow.
In 1980 Dr. Gehrels started the Spacewatch Project (a program to find dangerous asteroids and to keep them from hitting the earth), this program still uses the telescopes at Steward Observatory and Kitt Peak to survey the sky for asteroids and comets. He was also the founder of the highly recommended Space Science Series which was published by the University of Arizona Press. Gehrels was the editor for the first 30 volumes of the series.
Tom Gehrels was a part of the Dutch resistance during World War II and his brother died at the Dora concentration camp where the VI and V2 rockets were built toward the end of the war. In 1994 he was asked by the journal Nature to write a book review on the biographical memoir Wernher Von Braun: a Crusader for Space. The book praised the life of Wernhen Von Braun as the father of the American Space Program. In his review Gehrel’s claimed the authors glazed over the fact that Von Braun was also the Rocket Czar for Nazi Germany and responsible for the suffering and death of hundreds of thousands of people. Tom Gehrels also claims that Von Braun played a role in extending the life of the Third Reich, as well as World War II.
In the latter part of his career Dr. Gehrels focused on the research of cosmology and universal evolution. He published an original paper on the subject titled The Multiverse and Origin of our Universe
In 2007, the American Astronomical Society's Division for Planetary Sciences presented Gehrels with the Harold Masursky Award for meritorious service to planetary science. In April 2011, Gehrels was honored for his 50 years of service at the annual University of Arizona Service Awards luncheon.
Tom Gehrels was the husband of Aleida J. Gehrels (née de Stoppelaar) and father of Neil Gehrels, George Gehrels and Jo-Ann Gehrels. He died in Tucson, Arizona on July 11, 2009 at age 86. He was devoted to yoga and hiking as well as an active member of Greenpeace and the Humane Farming Association (HFA).
Tom’s interests included environmental, political, and humanitarian issues.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into twelve series.
Series I:Personal Files, 1952-2011,
Series II: Correspondence, 1962-1996
Series III: Publication Files, 1958-2006
Series IV: Research Files, 1894-1973
Series V: Travel files, 1973-2012
Series VI: Instructional files/Courses –Class notes, 1969-2001
Series VII: Photographs, circa 1992-1993
Series VIII: Newspaper Clippings, circa 1973-1999
Series IX: Slides, undated
Series X: Audio Visual materials, undated
Series XI: 3.5 Disks, undated
Series XII: CD's, 2005-2010
Scope and Content Note
Papers 1894-2010 (bulk 1960-2000). This collection consists of the professional and some personal papers of Tom Gerhels. The bulk of the material consists of his correspondence with other astronomers, scientists, state and federal politicians. There are also scholarly files, research files, and personal interest files. Almost all amassed during his fifty year career at the Lunar Planetary Laboratory and the Department of Planetary Sciences, University of Arizona. Other items in the collection are environmental files, travel files, instructional files, newspaper clippings, photographs, slides, film, computer disks and CDs.
Gerard Peter Kuiper Papers, MS 480; Michael J. Drake Papers, MS 511; Charles P. Sonett Papers, MS 520.
Access Terms
Gehrels, Tom, 1924-2011.
Von Braun, Wernher, 1912-1977
McMillan, Robert S.
Kuiper, Gerard P. (Gerard Peter), 1905-1973.
Coyne, George V.,1933-
Meinel, Aden B.
Pioneer (Space Probes)
Balloon--History
Astronomy
Planetary Sciences--History
Comets
Photometry
Polarization
Asteroids.
Solar system
India
University of Arizona--Department of Planetary Science--History.
United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration--History.
Dora Concentration camp.
Container List
- Series I: Biographical, 1924-1973.
  This series contains 2 subseries. Subseries 1 contains personal files including his individual interests, family tree, his involvement with Catalina Vista Neighborhood board, personal photographs, the family vacation to Lake Powell in 1963 and his sabbatical in 1970. Subseries 2 includes some of his college class notebooks when he was a student from 1950-1956.
  - Subseries 1: Personal files, 1961-2005
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    - Tom Gehrel’s annual faculty evaluations and other personal data, 1993-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Catalina Vista Neighborhood (Campbell and Grant), 1961-2011 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - China Watch Committee to end the Chinese Gulag, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Gehrels family tree, 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Interests; Environmental, Humanitarian and Political, 1990-2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Lake Powell vacation, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Log book/Employees, 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous items include but not limited to Pioneer patches and awards: For the NASA Medal for Exceptional Scientific Achievement - See box 28, circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Personal photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Sabbatical, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Tsunami fund raiser, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - University of Arizona Lunar Planetary Laboratory / Department of Planetary Sciences, 1969-1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 2: Tom Gehrel’s college class notebooks:, 1950-1956.
    Subseries contains his notebooks as graduate student while earning his masters and doctorate degrees.
    - Advanced Calculus, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Stellar Variability, 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Stellar Interiors, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Photographic Astronomy and Practical Astronomy, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Practical Astronomy and Practical Photometry, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Optics, 1952, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Solar Systems taught by Dr. Kuiper, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Optics, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Solar Systems and Celestial Mechanics, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Basic Astrophysics, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Spectral Classification and Stellar Astronomy, Winter 1954 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Radio Astronomy, Electronics, Optics, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Basic Astrophysics, 1954; 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Atmospheres II, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Stellar Spectroscopy and Photometry, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Solar System, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Unknown, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Photometry – Instruments, circa 1950’s (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Unknown, circa 1950’s (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Radio Astronomy, circa 1950’s (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Elementary Astronomy, circa 1950’s (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Unknown, circa 1950’s (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Unknown, circa 1950’s (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Unknown, circa 1950’s (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1961-2005
  This series is arranged alphabetically. It includes people and organizations (incoming and outgoing),
  - Subseries 1: Personal, 1961-2005
    - A, 1963-1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Akasofu, S.I., 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Alfven, Hannes, 1969-1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - American Program Bureau, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - B, 1961-1999 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Babbitt, Bruce, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Barr Engineering Arts, 1991-1993 (Boc 2, Folder 15)
    - Batavian Society for Experimental Philosophy, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Berkowitz, Francine, 1980, 1980-1996 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Bernhard, C.C., 1974-1982 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Berry, William O., 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Bhattachryya, Jagadish, 1980-1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Bijleveld, Wim, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Binzel, Richard P., 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Black, Robert, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Bok, Bart and Priscilla, 1967-1981 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Burns, Joseph, 1974-1981 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - C, 1958-2005 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Carter, Jimmy, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Chandrasekhar, Subrahmanyan, 1977-1995 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Chen Raphael, 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Clarke, Arthur C., 1971-1995 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Clinton, Bill, 1992-2002 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Coffeen, David L., undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Coyne, George V., 1964-1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Cruikshank, Dale, 1969-1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Cunningham, Clifford, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Cusanovich, Michael A., 1990, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - D, 1967-2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - DeConcini, Dennis, 1977-1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Degewig, Johan, 1975-1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Deinse, P.A.V., 1972-1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Devorkin, David (History of the U.S. Space Program - Von Braun), 1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Deshpande, Mohan R., 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Dollfus, Audouin, 1971-1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Doose, Lyn, 1970-1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Drake, Michael, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Drees, W., 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Dubinsky, Wendy and Richard, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Dutch TV, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - E, 1961-1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Edmondson, Frank, 1956-1993 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Encyclopedia of Planetary Sciences, 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Encyclopedia of Space Science and Technology, 1998-2002 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - F, 1963-1996 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Feng, Da Sheng, 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Fernando, Mervyn (Fathera), 1983-1995 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Frecker, Jack E., 1987-1993 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - G, 1964-1998 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Geake, J.E., 1982-1990 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Gehrels Family, 1974-1999 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Goodwin, Richard (Spacewatch Council), 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Goebel, Greg, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Goldberg, Leo, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Goldwater, Barry, 1971-1983 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Goodyear Aircraft Corporation, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - H, 1959-2008 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Halperin, Israel, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Hameen-Anttila, Jyrki, 1964-1972 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Hapke,Bruce.W., 1993 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Harris, Alan, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Harvill, Richard A., 1962-1983 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Hays, Daniel P., 1974-1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Herget, Paul, 1962-1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Herrick, Samuel, 1970-1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Hidajat, Bambang, 1974-1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Hubbard, W.B., 1976-1986 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Hughes, Howard, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - I, 1958-1997 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Inamori Foundation (Kyoto Prize), 1958-1997 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Ingeborg, Beugel, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - J, 1968-1995 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Jedicke, Robert, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - K, 1959-1999 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Karth, Joseph E., circa 1968 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Kassander, A.R., 1961-1979 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Kaufman, Max, 1961-1979 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Kenknight, Ken E., 1966-1992 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Kennedy, Harold D., 1977-1984 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Kitt Peak National Observatory (KPNO), 1961-1989 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Koffler, Henry, 1983-1990 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Kojima, Takuo, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Kogure, T., 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Kolokolova, Antonina, 1992-1997 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Koppeschaar, Carl, 1951, 1991-1998 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Ksanfomality, Leonid, 1980-1993 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Kuiper, Gerard, 1958-1973 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - L, 1962-1997 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - L 5 Society, 1982, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Lal, Devendra, 1971-1984 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Levenson, Nancy A., 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Levy, Eugene, H., 1983-1993 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - M, 1962-1997 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Mark, Hans, 1982-1998 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Marinus, Shirley, 1987-1996 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Marsden, Brian G., 1969-1997 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Mathews, Mildred Shapley, 1971-1994 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Mathews, Robert, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - McCain, John, 1993-1999 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - McMillan, Robert S., 1980-1997 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Meinel, Aden B., 1963-1997 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Merline, William J., 1982-1995 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Miles, Richard, 1989-1992 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - N, 1963-2001 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA), 1965, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - National Geographic Society, 1980-1993 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - O, 1966-1999 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Owings, Mrs., 1962-1965 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - P, 1959-2000 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - P, 1959-2000 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Pacheco, Manuel T., 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Panchal, Vikrau, 1986-1992 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Paster, Ed, 1992-1998 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Phillips Laboratory, Kirtland Air Force Base, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Pioneer Missions, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Ponnamperunia, 1980-1984 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Postma, Hans, 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Powell, Cory, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Prassanna, A.R., 1982 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Priest, M.R., 1959-1961 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Prince Bernhard of the Netherlands, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Q, 1971, 1986, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - R, 1958-1998 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Rabe, Eugene K., 1954-1995 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Rabinowitz, David L., 1989-1998 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Radoski, Henry, 1991-1996 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Rawal, J.J., 1980-1990 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Remo, John L., 1994-1996 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Research Corporation, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Rickman, Hans, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Roalstad, D.A. (Ball Aerospace), 1985 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Roamer, Elizabeth, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Roland, E.H., 1957-1982 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Rosenblatt, Paul, 1977, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - S, 1944-2005 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Saddeev, R.Z., 1979-1984 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Sagan, Carl, 1972-1994 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Sato, Takeski, 1980-1999 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Schaefer, John, 1971-1978 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Schreve, Guide, 1995-1997 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Schubart, Jaochim, 1972-1974; 1980 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Shoemaker, Eugene M., 1983-1996 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Shubina, Ksenia and Irina, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Sidharth, B.G., 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Singer, Fred, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Singer, Fred, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Sonett, Charles, 1974-1977 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Steel, Duncan, 1993-1997 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Steward Observatory, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Strittmatter, Peter (Space Watch Camera), 1984-1991 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Strong, J.D., 1961-1969 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - T, 1973-1998. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Tapia-Perez, Santiago, 1976-1991 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Thirunagari, Aruna, 1980-1983 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Tholen, David J., 1981-1993 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Titulaer, Chriet, 1974-1990 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Tohono O’odham Nation and Space Camp, 1998-1999. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Tomlinson, Gary W., 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Tyers, Kathy, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - U, 1964 -1996 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - United Nations, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - United States, Naval Observatory, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - University of Arizona, 1974-2005 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - V, 1966-2000 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Vaidyanath, Rajash, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Van Biesbroeck, Georges A., 1963-1991 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Van der Hucht, K.A., 1963-1991 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Van Houten, C.J. and Ingrid, 1961-1974 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Van Houten, C.J. and Ingrid, 1975-1984 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Varma, R.K., 1989-1992 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - W, 1962-1994 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Waland, Robert L., 1988-1995 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Weissman, Paul R., 1973, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Weitbrecht, Robert H., 1958-1983 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Weymann, Ray, 1970-1974 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Wickramasinghe, Chandra, 1967-1972 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Winzen, Otto C., 1962-1976 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Wisniewski, Wieslaw, 1986-1990 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Wolff, Milo, 1970-2001 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Wrubel, Marshal, 1961-1966 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Wood, John, 1958-1981 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Worden, S.P., 1994-1999 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Woxtep Mapraphte (Rita), undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - X-Y, 1967-1991 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Z, 1962-1995 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Zellner, Ben, 1968-1987 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Ziegler, Kenneth W., 1984 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Ziegler, Kenneth W., 1984 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Unknown, undated (Box 6, Folder 38)
- Series III: Scholarly Files
  This series is arranged alphabetically. It’s a record of Dr. Gehrels writing career. This series is divided into 7 subseries: 1. Articles, lectures, presentations 2. papers; presentations by year; 3. conferences, and workshops; 4. books; 5. book chapters; 6. book reviews; 7. The Space Science Series.
  - Subseries 1: Articles, talks, lectures, presentations and 1 Interview, 1958-2000
    - The Absence of Satellites of Asteroids, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - A Space Age Approach to Advanced Textbooks, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Asteroids and Comets near the Earth, 1980-81 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Asteroids are Dangerous, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - The Attraction of Comets and Asteroids, circa 1993-1995 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - The Beauty and Danger of Comets and Asteroids (lecture), 2001 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - The Beauty and Danger of Comets and Asteroids (article), 1993-1995 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Birth Statistics of a Population that Works Seasonally, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Brains, Courage and Integrity, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - CCD Scanning for Asteroids and Comets, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - College of France lectures, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Comets and Particles, December 1978 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Concepts of Universal Evolution I, II, III, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - The Convectively Unstable Atmosphere of Jupiter, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - The Cosmological Constants (response letter), undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - The Cutting Age of Astronomy in Arizona, May 1989 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Danger from Comets and Asteroids, circa 1993 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Detection of Near Earth Objects, 1995, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Dust and Rocks. V. Cometary Particles near Jupiter– unpublished, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Faint comet searching, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Finding the killer asteroids, the astronomer’s responsibility, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Fundamentals of cosmic physics, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - A Historical note on two Indian instruments, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - A Hydro-electric plant near Jayapura, undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - The Imaging photopolarimeter experiment on Pioneer II, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Interstellar polarization, circa 1960’s (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - It was the multiverse that evolved our physics with dark matter, 1990-2000 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Killer comets and asteroids …, undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Mechanical coordinate converter, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Midcourse maneuver and extraterrestrial communication for an encounter by Pioneer 10, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - A Minor planet called Geographos, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Minor planets I. The Rotation vesta, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Minor planets II. Photographic magnitudes, 1958; 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Minor planets III. Light curves of trojan asteroids, 1967-1969 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Minor planets IV. Color changes with distance from the sun, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Minor planets and related objects. IV. Asteroid 1566 Icarus, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Minor planets and related objects. VII. asteroid 1971 FA (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Minor planets and related objects. XXI. Photometry of eight asteroids, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Minor planets and related objects. XXII. Phase functions for (6) Hebe, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Minor planets and related objects. XXVI: Magnitudes for numbered asteroids, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Minor planets and related objects. XXVIII. Asteroids magnitudes and phase relations, 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - A Model of the lunar surface, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - A New method for making advances test books, 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - On the capabilities of the spin-scan imaging technique, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - On the feasibility of observing small asteroids with the Galileo, Venus, and comet rendezvous asteroid flyby missions, 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - On the future of mankind, 1973-1975 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - The Orientation of the rotation axis of Uranus, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 8)